

Enrico Liscio

PhD researcher

Personal Details

Date of birth 20/09/1993

e-mail e.liscio@tudelft.nl

Website enricoliscio.github.io

Personal Description

I truly believe that AI is an outstanding technology that can and must be used to help society progress. So that is what I set out to do: **research and develop** AI that can support us in better understanding each other. And I enjoy **divulging** it with videos for lay-people. Furthermore, as an actor and board member of an improvisational theatre association, I learned **organizational** and **communication** skills. Curiosity keeps me alive: **learning** something new brightens my days.

Working Experience

2024–present **Postdoctoral researcher**, *TU Delft & University of Amsterdam*, Understand how morality and human values are portrayed in media.

2020–2024 **PhD researcher**, *TU Delft*, Context-Specific Value Inference via Hybrid Intelligence: NLP methods to guide Al agents to estimate human values in a human-Al society.

Visiting PhD researcher, IIIA-CSIC and University of Barcelona, International cross-topic collaboration to lay out the foundations of value inference in sociotechnical systems (see AAMAS '23 publication). Sponsored by TAILOR Connectivity fund.

2017–2020 **Technical Lead & Deep learning developer**, *Fizyr*, Delft RoboValley, development of deep learning vision algorithms for the automation and logistics industry.

2016–2017 **Graduate intern**, *Heemskerk Innovative Technology*, Delft RoboValley, development of autonomous robotic grasping of objects in cluttered environments.

Education

2020–2024 Cum laude PhD, TU Delft.

Interactive Intelligence group, Intelligent Systems department

- 2015–2017 **Cum laude MSc**, *TU Delft*, *Final grade: 9/10*. Systems and Control (with the Robotics Institute Excellence Scholarship)
- 2012–2015 **Cum laude BSc**, *Università degli studi di Bologna*, *Final grade: 110L/110*. Automation Engineering

Publications

- 2024 J. Park*, E. Liscio*, P.K. Murukannaiah. Morality is Non-Binary: Building a Pluralist Moral Sentence Embedding Space using Contrastive Learning. In Findings of EACL '24, St. Julian's, Malta, ACL, 654-673.
- 2024 R. Lera-Leri, **E. Liscio**, F. Bistaffa, C.M. Jonker, M. Lopez-Sanchez, P.K. Murukannaiah, J.A. Rodriguez-Aguilar, F. Salas-Molina. Aggregating Value Systems for Decision Support. In *Knowledge-Based Systems*, 287, 111453.
- 2024 M. van der Meer, E. Liscio, C.M. Jonker, A. Plaat, P. Vossen, P.K. Murukannaiah. A Hybrid Intelligence Method for Argument Mining. In *Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research*, 80, 1187-1222.
- 2023 E. Liscio, O. Araque, L. Gatti, I. Constantinescu, C.M. Jonker, K. Kalimeri, P.K. Murukannaiah. What does a Text Classifier Learn about Morality? An Explainable Method for Cross-Domain Comparison of Moral Rhetoric. In ACL '23, Toronto, Canada, ACL, 14113-14132.
- 2023 E. Liscio, R. Lera-Leri, F. Bistaffa, R.I.J. Dobbe, C.M. Jonker, M. Lopez-Sanchez, J.A. Rodriguez-Aguilar and P.K. Murukannaiah. Value Inference in Sociotechnical Systems: Blue Sky Ideas Track. In AAMAS '23, London, UK, IFAAMAS, 1774-1780.
- 2023 E. Liscio, R. Lera-Leri, F. Bistaffa, R.I.J. Dobbe, C.M. Jonker, M. Lopez-Sanchez, J.A. Rodriguez-Aguilar and P.K. Murukannaiah. Inferring Values via Hybrid Intelligence: Poster Track. In HHAI '23, Munich, Germany, IOS Press, 373-378.
- 2023 **E. Liscio**, O. Araque, L. Gatti, I. Constantinescu, C.M. Jonker, K. Kalimeri, P.K. Murukannaiah. Tomea: an Explainable Method for Comparing Morality Classifiers across Domains. In *BNAIC '23*, *Delft, the Netherlands*, 1-4.
- 2022 E. Liscio, M. van der Meer, L.C. Siebert, C.M. Jonker, and P.K. Murukannaiah. What Values Should an Agent Align with? An Empirical Comparison of General and Context-Specific Values. Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems, 36(23):32.
- 2022 E. Liscio, A.E. Dondera, A Geadău, C.M. Jonker, and P.K. Murukannaiah. Cross-Domain Classification of Moral Values. In Findings of NAACL '22, Seattle, USA, ACL, 2727-2745, [Reproducibility badge (top 3%)].
- 2022 **E. Liscio**, C.M. Jonker, and P.K. Murukannaiah. Identifying Context-Specific Values via Hybrid Intelligence: Poster Track. In *HHAI '22*, Amsterdam, IOS Press, 298-301, [Best poster award].
- 2022 M. van der Meer, **E. Liscio**, C.M. Jonker, A. Plaat, P. Vossen, and P.K. Murukannaiah. HyEnA: A Hybrid Method for Extracting Arguments from Opinions. In *HHAI* '22, Amsterdam, IOS Press, 17-31, [Best paper award].
- 2022 L.C. Siebert, E. Liscio, P.K. Murukannaiah, L. Kaptein, S.L. Spruit, J. van den Hoven, and C.M. Jonker. Estimating Value Preferences in a Hybrid Participatory System. In HHAI '22, Amsterdam, IOS Press, 114-127, [Best paper award finalist].

- 2021 E. Liscio, M. van der Meer, L.C. Siebert, C.M. Jonker, N. Mouter, and P.K. Murukannaiah. Axies: Identifying and Evaluating Context-Specific Values. In AAMAS '21, Online, IFAAMAS, 799-808.
- 2021 **E. Liscio**, M. van der Meer, C.M. Jonker, and P.K. Murukannaiah. A Collaborative Platform for Identifying Context-Specific Values: Demonstration Track. In *AAMAS* '21, *Online*, IFAAMAS, 1773-1775.

Awards

- 2022 **TAILOR Connectivity Scholarship**, Research visit scholarship, EU Horizon 2020.
- 2022 Best Paper Award, HHAI '22.
- 2022 Best Poster Award, HHAI '22.
- 2015–2017 Excellence Scholarship, TU Delft Robotics scholarship, Robotics institute.
- 2011–2014 Excellence Scholarship, ENASARCO scholarship, ENASARCO.

Invited Talks

- 2024 Natural Language Processing for (un)structured Data Analysis, *Red Cross* 510, the Hague.
- 2023 **The Impact of AI on Architecture**, *BNA (Dutch National Architect Association) Architect Day*, Amsterdam.
- 2023 **Understanding Humans' Values in a Human-Al Society**, *TAILOR WP3 Work-shop*, European Network for Trustworthy Artificial Intelligence, online.
- 2022 Estimating Context-Specific Values from Natural Language, NCSU AI in Society, North Carolina, USA [video].
- 2021 Estimating Human Values from Language, IIIA-CSIC, Barcelona [video].

Reviewer

- 2024 AAMAS '25, ARR 06/24, C-MAS '24, EXTRAAMAS '24,.
- 2023 AAMAS '24, ARR 10-12/23, DWMV '24, ACM Comp. Surv., Inf. Syst. Front.
- 2022 AAMAS '23 (Blue Sky Ideas Track), AIES '23, ECAI '23, VALE '23.

Teaching

2022-2024 **Introduction to Artificial Neural Networks**, *Part of the CSE2530 Computational Intelligence course in the BSc Computer Science*, TU Delft.

Conferences

- 2024 **EACL, EDDY**, Lead author and presenter.
- 2023 ACL, AAMAS, BNAIC, Lead author and presenter.
- 2022 NAACL, HHAI, Lead author and presenter.
- 2021 **AAMAS**, Lead author and presenter.

Organization

2023-current **Deliberation and Argumentation seminar series**, *Co-organizer*, HI Consortium.

2023-current Citizen-Centric Al Systems seminar series, Co-organizer, CCAIS.

2020 BNAIC '20, Volunteer, Online.

Expertise

NLP	••••	Linux	••••	Illustrator	••••
Ethi	cs ••••	Python	••••	InDesign	••••
XAI	••••	PyTorch	••••	₽T Γ Χ	••••

Languages

Italian Mothertongue

English IELTS Certificate - 7.5/9 Professionally fluent - C1 level

French Diplôme d'études en langue française (DELF) Can understand and speak - B1 level

Extra-Curricular Activities

2024-current **Dad**, home, frontline.

2021–2024 **Volleyball**, *Inter Rijswijk*, player.

2015–2020 Improvisational theater, Delft Improv Group, improviser.

2016–2018 **Board member**, *Delft Improv Group*, chairman.

2016–2018 Volleyball/Basketball, D.S.V.V. Punch, player.

2016 Coach, TU Delft, introducing new students to the university.